-
-=
-= L
-= LU
-= LUO
-= LUO M
-= LUO MA
-= LUO MAD
-= LUO MADE
-= LUO MADE D
-= LUO MADE DV
-= LUO MADE DVD
-= LUO MADE DVD =
-= LUO MADE DVD =-
Mouna! Take it easy!
莫那！別急…
A good hunter waits patiently
好獵人要懂得等待時機…
Out of the way! Let me do it!
走開！讓我來！
Move!
讓開！
Mouna! Mouna!
莫那…莫那…
Mouna, be careful!
莫那…小心…
Mouna!
莫那…
Mouna,
here come the Bununs from Kntabang Clan!
莫那，干卓萬人來了…
Let's go! Come on!
快跑啊！快點！
Come on, let's go! Leave the boar!
快跑，山豬不要了！
There he is!
人在那邊！
Kill him!
快打死他…
Mouna, get down!
莫那，躲下去！
Over there!
在那邊…
Mouna is over there! -Shoot him!
-莫那跑出來了…
-開槍！
Come on! Hurry!
走！快點！
Listen to me! My name is Mouna Rudo!
聽好了，我叫莫那魯道！
Be alert when you hear this name again!
以後聽到這個名字要小心了！
Who?
是誰？
Who becomes the hero?
是誰當英雄了嗎？
Who is it?
到底是誰呀？
Your Mouna is back!
你們家莫那回來了…
It's your Mouna! He's back!
是你們家莫那…是你們家莫那…
It's Mouna!
是莫那呀！
Mouna is a true man now
莫那是真正的男人了…
Mouna is back!
莫那回來了…
Well done, Mouna!
好一個莫那呀！
A true man is back!
真正的男人回來了！
The hero is back!
英雄回家了…
Mouna..
莫那！
you've offered blood sacrifice
to our ancestors' spirits
你已經血祭了祖靈
I hereby tattoo the marks of manhood
on your face
我在你臉上刺上男人的記號
From now on..
從今以後…
you shall abide by our ancestral spirit
遵守祖律的約束
to guard our clan and our hunting grounds
守護部落
守護獵場
On the rainbow bridge
在彩虹橋上…
our ancestors' spirits await the reunion
with your valiant soul
祖靈將等侯你英勇的靈魂
Warriors of The Rainbow I : Sun Flag
(In 1895)
(the island of Taiwan was ceded to Japan)
(under the Treaty of Shimonoseki
between Japan and China)
The island of Taiwan
is the new territory of our empire
台灣島是帝國的新版圖
yet to receive our Mikado's grace
未浴皇恩之地
The islanders are warlike innately
雖然島上的人民好逞兇鬥狠
It's said that they're armed to fight us
據聞已經武裝要抵抗我軍接收
but they're a scattered bunch,
nothing to be afraid of
但盡是散兵游勇，無需畏懼！
Once disembarked at Keelung Port
基隆港登陸之後…
we must sweep the entire island with force
由北至南全面掃蕩
We must prevent any disrespect
from the people
必須使島民不再有狎侮之心
so as to gain their wholehearted allegiance
to our empire of the sun
誠心臣服在我太陽帝國之下…
Especially the heartland of Taiwan
occupied by the tribal savages
特別是由蕃族割據的心臟地帶
There are ample resources
of lumber and mines in the mountains
這裡的高山，林產、礦產…
Endless treasures..
無限的寶藏呀…
Father, last night I dreamt of a deer
with white spots around its eyes..
父親…昨晚我夢到一隻鹿…
一隻眼睛有白色斑紋的鹿唷…
Sisin babblers are singing an auspicious song
祖靈鳥唱吉利的歌了！
Go ahead and hunt the deer in your dream
去追獵你夢中的鹿吧！
...for your own wedding
來一場豐盛的婚禮吧！
Wait! Hold on!
等一下…等一下喔…
Hold on!
等一下喔…
Charge!
衝啊！
Hold on!
等一下等一下…
Charge!
攻擊！
Let's kill them!
…跟他拚啦！
That was the deer in my dream
這頭是我夢中的鹿！
Listen to me!
大家聽我說…
Dance! Let's dance!
跳舞吧！用力跳！
Everyone Dance!
跳到不能動吧！
Come and dance, my in-law!
親家，起來跳舞呀！
Come on, everyone! Let's dance!
所有人呀…都跳起來！
This is my son Mouna Rudo
這是我的兒子莫那魯道！
The bravest and strongest warrior
in Mehebu Clan
馬赫坡最勇猛剽悍的勇士
He'll be an unparalleled chief
將來一定是部落的大領袖
You're wise to marry your daughter to him
你把女兒嫁給他是非常明智的
Dance! Let's dance!
用力跳！用力呀！
Let's cheer for them!
大家都替他們開心啊！
Be joyful, everyone!
大家都要開心啊！
Out of the way!
靠邊點…
Stand clear of the path please
大家配合一下…
Out of the way! Please!
靠邊靠邊一點！拜託！
Out of the way!
靠邊一點啦！
Out of the way! Move!
靠邊點…配合一點…靠邊…
Out of the way please!
靠邊點…拜託一下…
Hey, my old friend!
老朋友！
Oh no! It's him again
糟糕…怎麼又是這個傢伙…
My old friend!
老朋友！
You from Mehebu Clan! Over here!
馬赫坡的…這裡…
Over here!
這裡…
Hey, boss!
老闆！
Come
來啊！
Must you wear such a big head
on that small head of yours?
頭小小一個，帽子戴這麼大頂…
My old friend!
老朋友！
Mouna?
莫那…
Seediqs from Toda
-You from Tnbarah Clan, over here!
道澤人…
屯巴拉的…這裡…
Hey, young man, don't you make trouble here
年輕人…
不要在我這裡亂來喔…
The tallest one is Mouna Rudo
of Mehebu Clan from Tgdaya
那最高的就是馬赫坡的莫那魯道…
You've come all the way here
with so little meat for exchange?
走那麼遠的路
Those of you from Toda are so shameless
就只帶這麼一點點獵物來交易？
道澤人還真的不怕丟臉…
Why don't you offer your
hunting grounds to us for free?
乾脆把獵場送我們吧！
Mouna Rudo, don't be too proud
I'm not afraid of you
莫那魯道…你別囂張
我沒有在怕你！
Mouna Rudo, I'm Temu Walis
莫那魯道！我是鐵木瓦力斯
I'll cut your head off when I grow up
我長大一定獵下你人頭！
Temu Walis?
鐵木瓦力斯？
You won't have the chance to grow up
…我不會讓你長大的！
Is that Temu Cire?
那個是鐵木奇萊嗎？
No, it's Temu Walis
是鐵木瓦力斯吧！
I mean that grown-up man
我問的是那個男人！
I don't know. Not someone famous, I guess
不知道！應該不太有名吧…
Gather up, young men!
年輕人集合…
Come on! Bring your weapons!
快！年輕人帶上武器！
Come with us! Quick!
跟我們來！快點！
Put these away!
收起來！
Quick! All young men come with us!
快點…年輕人都過來…
Run!
快跑！
Temu!
鐵木…
Mouna!
莫那…
Mouna, he's one of our own
莫那，你打到自己人了…
No one can ever run ahead of me, you hear?
任何人都不准跑在我的前面…
聽到沒有！
Come on, Labay!
快點…拉拜…
Are you alright?
沒事吧！
Laying railway tracks?
鋪設鐵道？
It's no easy task in the mountains
在山裡鋪鐵道可不容易啊…
In order to harvest the natural resources
in those forests
山地森林產業要開發
we need to have proper transportation
交通不做不行…
Yeah
是啊…
It's a shame to leave
those resources undeveloped
雖說山區豐富的資源不開發可惜…
but those savages up there..
不過山上的生蕃…
Sir?
長官…
Here she is, sir
長官，人來了！
She dares not lead you past Hakaw Supeitei,
Captain
大尉，他只敢帶你們到人止關
She'll spend the night in her father's house
in Meisi
然後她在她的眉溪老家過夜
She won't accompany you to
the hunting grounds of other clans
不敢再和你們進去其他部落的獵場
Much obliged
麻煩你了！
Let's go!
出發了！
Captain?
大尉…
Those savages in the mountains
are rather ferocious
山上的生蕃很凶…
Please be careful!
你們要小心啊！
Hey!
喂…
Hey, it's your turn now
喂，該你了…
Wow! How beautiful!
哇…好漂亮啊…
Yes, indeed
是啊…
It was so dark last night
昨晚夜黑…
that we didn't notice we're surrounded
by cherry blossom trees
竟然不知道睡在這美麗的櫻花林
Cherry blossoms?
櫻花？
They really are cherry blossoms
真的是櫻花！
It's so red
好紅…
Red as blood
像血一樣的紅櫻花…
Blockade the entire Wushe region
封鎖霧社！
Ban all trading between the Hans
and the Wushe savages
禁止漢人與霧社蕃的一切交易！
Yes, sir
是…
Back off!
後退！後退！
Put down your weapons! Go up there!
把槍放下！過去那邊！
Hurry up!
動作快一點！
Come on!
走快一點！
It's an ambush! Watch out!
有突擊…小心…
Hide there! Quick!
先躲起來…快！
They're up there!
在那邊…
Uwe! Uwe!
巫黑…巫黑…
Retreat!
退…撤退！
There's no way out!
不行啊！退不出去啊…
These intruders are out of their minds
這些異族人真是不要命了…
How dare they show up at my doorstep
膽敢進到我部落門口…
Throw them down!
全部推下去！
Get out of here! Quick!
快逃…快逃…
Hurry up!
快一點！
Follow me!
跟我走！
I see. I see
知道了…知道了…
I see
知道了…
(A Short Account of Taiwan)
Give me their biggest enemy
他們最大的敵人是誰？
There they are!
他們在那邊！
Hello
你好啊！
你好！
Here
給你…
The intruders don't allow
the Hans to deal with us
異族人不讓漢人和我們交易
But we can deal with you, can't we?
難道我們就不會和你們交易嗎？
Idiots!
笨蛋…
Bring me the wine!
拿酒來！
Bring the wine!
拿酒…拿酒呀…
Drink!
喝！
Look! I'm Mouna Rudo
你看！
I killed at Hakaw Supeitei a chief
of the intruders
我莫那魯道在人止關殺的…
可是異族頭目哪！
Mouna Rudo?
莫那魯道…
You're Mouna Rudo?
你就是莫那魯道…
Yes, I am
我！莫那魯道！
Mouna Rudo!
莫那.魯道！
Chief? Chief?
頭目…頭目…
Where is Mouna Rudo?
莫那魯道在哪裡？
I couldn't get him drunk
…這個傢伙一直灌不醉！
Wake up!
醒來…快醒來！
Those Bununs from Kntabang Clan
are hunting heads
干卓萬人出草了！
Get up! Let's go!
起來！快逃啊！
Let's get out of here! Hurry!
快逃…快呀！
All the human beings on this land
活在這大地的人呀…
The gods bestow upon us a mortal life
神靈為我們編織了有限的生命…
But we are true men indeed
可是我們是真正的男人人唷！
A true man dies in the battlefield
真正的男人死在戰場上…
and he strides to the heavenly home
of our ancestors
他們走向祖靈之家…
There lies a fertile hunting ground
祖靈之家有一座肥美的場唷！
that can only be guarded by a qualified true man
只有真正的男人
才有資格守護那個獵
When he arrives at the heavenly home
of our ancestors
當他們走向祖靈之家的時侯
he'll come across a beautiful rainbow bridge
會經過一座美麗的虹橋唷！
The ancestors' spirits guarding it say.
守橋的祖靈說：
''Let's take a look at your hands''
『來看看你的手吧！』
When the man opens his hands
男人攤開手…
we see bloodstains that can never be wiped clean
手上是怎麼也揉擦不去的血痕
''Now you're a true man indeed!''
says our ancestors' spirits
『果然是真正的男人呀！』
Come out, guys!
男人都出來…
Bring your weapons!
帶上武器了！
Come on!
快點…
''Go! Go ahead! My hero!''
『去吧！去吧！我的英雄！』
''Your soul may now enter
the heavenly home of our ancestors
『你的靈魂可以進入祖靈之家！』
''to guard the hunting ground of honor''
『去去守護那永遠的榮譽獵場吧！』
Stop it! It'll never be ignited
別吵了，點不著的…
And a true woman must be good
at weaving red coat of arms for her man
而真正的女人…
When she reaches the rainbow bridge
she opens her hands
是必須要善於編織紅色戰衣唷…
當她到達彩虹橋的時侯
showing her calluses that can never be removed
她攤開她的手…
手上是怎麼也揉擦不去的繭
''Go! Go ahead! You're a true woman''
『去吧！去吧！你是真正的女人！』
say the ancestors' spirits
guarding the rainbow bridge
守橋的祖靈這麼說：
''Your soul may now enter
the heavenly home of our ancestors
『你的的靈魂可以到達祖靈之家！』
''No go weave a rainbow-like dress for yourself!''
『為自己織一件如彩虹般的衣裳吧！』
Be careful! -Over there!
-小心…
-那邊…
Stop!
不要跑…
A man who's never decapitated an enemy
or a woman who's not good at weaving
沒有出草取過敵人首級的男人
is not qualified to have their faces tattooed
和不善於編織技藝的女人
是沒有資格在臉上紋上圖騰的
Some day, when they're gone
有一天，他們的靈魂走了
and their souls arrive at the rainbow bridge
到達彩虹橋接受驗證的時侯
the ancestors' spirits guarding it
would see their clean faces and ask.
守橋的祖靈看著他們…
How dare you bring a machete! Bastard!
乾淨沒有圖騰的臉
還敢帶刀…混蛋！
''Are these my children?''
『這是我的孩子嗎？』
''Are you my children?''
『你們是我的孩子嗎？…』
''Go back! Go back now!''
『回去！回去！回去吧！』
''You're not true Seediqs''
『你們不是真正的賽德克！』
''You're not qualified to enter
the heavenly home of our ancestors
『你們不夠資格進入祖靈之家！』
Run! Come on!
逃！快逃！
Let's get out of here!
快點逃…
Run, Mouna!
莫那快逃啊…
Just go!
別看了…
Rudo, are you alright?
魯道，還好嗎？
Father!
父親…
Suddenly, the tribesmen find themselves blowsy
他們霎時蓬首垢面
their eyes blank
魂魄茫然無神…
They turn around in shame
and walk though the rugged valleys
他們羞愧地繞過顛簸難行的溪谷
They become wailing ghosts
suffering unbearable pain
他們哀哭的鬼魂
from all the cuts
by the poisonous crabs along the creek
被守在溪谷的毒蟹剪得傷痛難忍…
Mouna..
莫那…
you must keep the intruders away from our clan
千萬不能讓異族人進到部落…
Mouna, do you understand?
莫那…我這樣說你懂了嗎？
Abide by our ancestral dictations
遵守祖律的規範
and be a Seediq Bale (a true man)
當一個真正的人
Excuse me, sir
長官…打擾一下…
Let's see..
跟您報告…
The first one from the left is Mouna Rudo
the chief of Mehebu Clan
最左邊的是馬赫坡頭目莫那魯道…
Those behind him are Ubus and Mouna Sine
然後…後面是烏布斯和摩那希尼
Mouna, stop glaring
莫那，不要看了
Look down
把頭低下來…
Mouna, stop glaring
莫那…別看了…
Ubus..
烏布斯…
our ancestors never lost
any of our hunting grounds in the past
我們祖先再怎樣也沒失去過獵場…
I can't believe these intruders
are taking them away from us now
而我們竟然讓異族人在這裡稱王！
I'll never submit to them
我不甘心…
I will never
These are all yours?
這些都是你殺的？
I will never!
我不甘心！
Mouna!
莫那…
Stop it!
不要動…
Mouna!
莫那…
Hurry up! It's going to rain
快點，要下雨了！
Awi!
阿威…
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Are you alright?
…還好嗎？
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Are you alright?
…還好嗎？
(Wushe, 1930)
Schools, clinics, grocery stores
教育所、醫療所、雜貨店…
post offices, hotels, boardinghouses..
郵局、旅館、宿舍…
We've managed to civilize
整個霧社地區的蕃族
all the Wushe savages
都已經被我們給文明化了
It's not an easy task
真是不容易啊！
Hard to imagine that this was once
the most uncivilized heartland here
很難想像這裡曾經是…
這島上最黑暗的心臟地帶呀！
Carrying logs..
他們扛著木頭
and walking from the lumberyard uphill to here
takes them a whole day, doesn't it?
從山上的製材場走到這裡…
Don't worry. These savages are strong
不就已經一整天嗎？
And they're more than happy
to earn some money for millet wine
沒關係…這些生蕃身強體壯
給他們幾個錢買酒就很高興了
Come on. This way please
來，請往這邊走…
Mr. Satsuka,
佐塚先生…
how long have you been in Wushe?
你到霧社這個地方多久了？
Over a decade
…都十幾年了…
So you know this region very well?
所以你對這裡非常瞭解囉？
Of course. My wife is a savage woman
當然…連我妻子都是蕃人了
I know this region like the back of my hand
-It's this bone right here
-我能不瞭解嗎？
-就這塊骨頭
It hurts so much when you press it
這樣壓就好痛…
Right here?
是這裡嗎？
Ah! Easy!
啊…你小力一點…
Here! Have a drink!
來！來…喝酒！喝酒！
No more wine for us please. We can't afford it
老闆，別再拿酒了
我們付不起錢呀！
It's alright
沒關係…沒關係…
This one's on me
下一碗再付錢啦！
You're indeed a beautiful serpent
老闆呀，你真是一隻美麗的蛇唷！
Every day I carry those damn logs
without getting paid properly
每天扛這種領不到錢的木頭
Now I'm so broke that even my hounds
look down on me
窮到連我的獵犬都瞧不起我了…
We're losing our hunting grounds
獵場都快沒了
and you still keep the hounds
to look down on you?
還留著獵犬來瞧不起人？
Those are the trees
that used to watch over our ancestors
Look!
你看！
那些看過我們祖先的樹…
This is how they end up
都變成這樣的木頭了…
Strange thing is, why so many constructions?
奇怪…怎麼有那麼多的工程啊？
What? Not only do you befriend us with wine
but you speak our language fluently
咦！你這個酒料蕃通
蕃話講得很標準嘛！
Hey! It's going to rain
喂！快下雨了
Stop drinking and go home!
-Good morning, sir!
-不回去還在這喝酒！
-大人好！
Good morning, Mr. Policeman
警察大人好…
You've worked all day long
for such a mean wage
辛辛苦苦扛了一天的木頭
and you waste it on wine?
才賺那麼點錢…還買酒！
What else can we do with so little money?
這些錢除了買酒還能做什麼？
Yeah, right! We're savages, aren't we?
對啦！我們是蕃人
We aren't supposed to know
anything about saving money
怎麼會懂得存錢呢？
Yeah, Mr. Policeman. You're Japanese, sir
對啦！警察大人
你是日本人呀！
You don't know how hard our lives are
你不瞭解我們蕃人的痛苦啊！
Only Mr. Wu here understands us
但是這個漢人老闆瞭解我們
He's a beautiful serpent
他是一隻美麗的蛇！
He's a viper!
…有毒的蛇唷！
Excuse me -Hello
-打擾了…
-你好！
I'd like some salt, please -No problem
-我要買鹽…
-好！好！
Oh no! It's raining! Hurry up and go home, sir
下雨了…
大人，你快走吧！
Or your glorious uniform will be soaking wet
別讓你這身榮耀的制服給淋濕了…
Go ahead!
走吧！走吧！
Go on!
走開啦！
Run, sir!
用跑的呀，大人！
Your Japanese fur is too precious to spoil
你那身日本毛皮可珍貴的哪…
It's raining
下雨了呀！
Go collect the laundry hanging outside
快先去把外面的衣服收進來…
Can't you tell what needs to be done first?
什麼事該先做也不知道…真難教…
Hey, come back!
Are you taking the baby out in the rain?
回來！
你要把孩子揹出去淋雨啊？
I'm sorry
對不起…
What an imbecile!
怎麼會笨成這樣啊…
Who'd marry such an idiot like you?
還想要結婚？
When it rains, it pours
這雨下得還真大呀！
Good morning
早安！
This is our policeman Hanaoka Jiro
這位是警手花岡二郎
This is our new police minister Ekawa Hakudo
這是新任警察課長江川博道先生
Jiro is a savage too
二郎也是一個蕃人！
Older brother
哥哥…
Older sister -Older sister
-姊姊…-姊姊…
Younger brother -Younger brother
-弟弟…-弟弟…
Younger sister -Younger sister
-妹妹…-妹妹…
Okay, one more time
好…再來一次！
Father -Father
-父親…-父親…
Mother -Mother
-母親…-母親…
Older brother -Older brother
-哥哥…-哥哥…
Older sister..
姊姊…
Hurry! She's in labor!
快快快…要生了…
Two savages
can never give birth to a Japanese child
就不信兩個蕃人能生出個日本孩子
Are you alright, Hanako?
花子，你還好嗎？
This job is for women only. What are you doing?
這是女人的工作，你幹嘛？…
Dakis, get out of here! Get out!
達奇斯，你出去…
快點出去！
Oh, what an extraordinary sight!
好特別的景象呀！
Timber!
樹倒了！
(Hark, people)
聽著吧！人們！
(Behold, people)
看著吧！人們！
(Oh, our warriors)
我們的勇士們！
(The youngsters
much like the budding pine leaves)
像松樹嫩芽的青年
(They show true bravery)
是真正的勇士啊！
(Fought in the falling leaves)
決死如紛飛的落葉
(Fought under the withered pine tree)
決死如乾枯的松枝
(Now they're back with heads hunted)
而今帶著首級歸來了…
(Our warriors fought with all their might)
像松葉決死般的勇士呀！
(Mahebu Police Station)
(馬赫坡駐在所)
Chief!
頭目…
Pawan, why aren't you in school?
巴萬…
今天怎麼沒有去上學！
I'm sick
我生病了！
Sick? But you don't look like sick
生病？
你怎麼可能會生病…
Did your teacher beat you?
老師打你嗎？
I raced a Japanese kid and I won
我跑步贏了一個日本小孩
And the kid was crying
結果那個日本小孩哭了
The teacher blamed me for bullying him,
so he beat me
老師說我欺負他，就打我…
Can I have another one please?
我可以再喝一杯嗎？
I'll win the race on the sports day
運動會那天，看我拿第一名
Those Japanese kids can cry their balls out
when they watch me getting awarded
讓那些日本孩子哭著看我領獎…
Chief, I hate the Japanese
頭目…
我討厭日本人…
Chief Mouna?
莫那頭目…
My grandpa said you were a hero
when you were younger
我祖父說你年輕時侯是個英雄…
Your grandpa said
I was a hero when I was younger?
你祖父說我年輕時侯是個英雄？
I'm still a hero. Does he know that?
那我現在還是個英雄，他知道嗎？
Chief Mouna, will you take me along
next time you go hunting?
莫那頭目…
這次打獵你可以帶我一起去嗎？
Pawan, where is your hunting ground?
巴萬，你的獵場在哪裡？
Chief Mouna!
莫那頭目…
I'm alright. Just a little bit tipsy, that's all
…沒事的！我只有一點點醉而已！
What the hell?
怎麼了呀？
Hanako!
花子…
Look what you have done!
你們是怎麼搬的木頭啊？…
How many times do I have to tell you
that you cannot drag these logs along?
叫你們不可以用拖的聽不懂嗎？
You destroyed the logs
-Only the bark is scratched
好好的木頭弄成這樣！
不過就皮壞掉而已…
The inside is still intact
裡面都還是好的呀！
How many times do I have to tell you?
You savages!
你們這些生蕃…
到底要講幾遍才懂啊？
What? You wanna fight?
怎樣？不服氣嗎？
The paths are slippery because of rain
下雨路那麼滑…
He nearly lost his life slipping down a slope
剛剛他差點摔死你知不知道！
Where is your log?
…你的木頭呢？
Slipped into the ravine -Slipped?
…滑掉了！
滑掉了？
Do you know how expensive it is?
你知道那一根木頭多貴嗎？
Pihu!
比荷！
Yoshimura!
吉村！
Chief Mouna..
莫那頭目…
Sir Yoshimura?
吉村大人
You're looking at me
at such a disrespectful angle
你用這麼沒禮貌的角度看我…
Aren't you afraid of being stabbed blind?
不怕我刺瞎你嗎？
Who do you think you are?
你以為你是誰啊？
You're not the boss here in Mehebu
馬赫坡的老大不是你…
I am!
是我…
You will not get paid today
今天別想領錢了！
The precious logs are destroyed
好好的木頭拖成這樣…
Do it again and you'll have to pay for the loss
下次再這樣，我還要你們賠！
Keep working! -With what?
-繼續工作啊！-賠什麼？
We get nothing from working for you
替你們工作又領不到錢
What do you want us to pay with? -Pihu!
還要賠你什麼？
比荷！
Chief Mouna, he... -I saw it
-莫那頭目，是他…
-我看見了！
Go home!
回去！
…回去！
Yoshimura, stop picking on them
吉村，你不要老是找他們麻煩…
You don't know nothing
你這菜鳥懂什麼？
I was educating them
我這是在教育呀！
These damn savages!
這些可惡的生蕃…
I'll have you pay for this some day
有一天要你們好看！
Good morning
早安…
早安！
Good morning
What? Checking out guns?
怎麼？來借槍啊？
Watan Robo is getting married
We've got some preparations to do
瓦旦要結婚了，得幫他準備呀！
Tado? Baso?
達多…巴索…
I heard your father Mouna Rudo
聽說你們父親莫那魯道
has mobilized lots of men for this hunt?
為了這次打獵出動了不少人？
Yeah, but what can we hunt
in those disappearing forests?
對啊！只是消失的森林哪來的獵物？
You've about hacked down all the trees
on our hunting grounds
獵場的樹已經快被你們砍光了
If we don't go hunting now
不趁現在去多打點獵物
we'll have nothing left
once the trees are all gone
將來樹沒了…
就什麼都沒了！
Tado Mouna!
達多莫那！
You'd better watch your mouth!
你講話給我小心一點！
Savages will always be savages
生蕃就是生蕃…
They have no manners at all
一點禮貌都沒有！
Wait!
等一下！
Pawan?
巴萬？
What is the kid doing there?
這小子在那邊幹嘛？
Pawan!
巴萬…
Chief Mouna! My hunting ground is right here!
莫那頭目
我的獵場在這裡呀！
Temu Walis?
鐵木瓦力斯…
You red-foot pheasant!
你這隻紅腳鳩…
Don't you know
this is the Mehebu hunting ground?
不知道這是我馬赫坡的獵場嗎？
Mouna! It's just a misunderstanding
莫那！莫那…
This is the first time my eldest son goes hunting
別誤會…
我大兒子第一次打獵
I asked Temu to bring me here
是我要鐵木帶我來的！
Mouna, I asked Temu to teach him
莫那，是我請鐵木來教他打獵的
Even so, you cannot trespass
into our Mehebu hunting ground
那也不應該跑進我馬赫坡的獵場！
This used to be our Toda hunting ground
在我叔父的時侯…
when my uncle was alive
這裡本來就是我們道澤的獵場
You Mehebu clansmen robbed it from us
是你們馬赫坡強佔去的！
Rob it back if you can -Enough!
你有本事就再搶回去啊！
夠了！
Mouna, can you do me this favor?
莫那…給我個面子可以嗎？
Favor?
面子？
Kojima..
小島…
if you lived in Mehebu now, I'd do you this favor
如果你現在在我馬赫坡…
我一定給足你面子！
But you live in Tnbarah Clan
但是你現在在屯巴拉
Take these red-foot pheasants
and get out of my hunting ground
就給我帶著這群紅腳鳩…
滾離我的獵場！
I don't care if it's your hunting ground or theirs
什麼你的獵場，我的獵場？
because everything here
belongs to us Japanese now
全部都是我們日本人的！
Temu, you just wait and see
鐵木…
你等著瞧…
Some day I'll destroy your Tnbarah Clan
有一天我殺進你們屯巴拉…
Go on and do it if you dare
帶種的話走進來一步看看！
Let's see who's killed first
看誰先幹掉誰！
I don't care if you're Mouna Rudo
莫那魯道又怎樣…
Wow, well done
好厲害喔…
Can a girl carry such a heavy load?
女孩子揹那麼重沒問題嗎？
Go! Go!
加油！加油…
Good girl!
好乖唷…
The men in your clan
are all out hunting, aren't they?
部落男人都出去打獵了是吧？
Wanna make some extra bucks?
要不要賺點外快？
Come with me to my boardinghouse! -No!
-陪我到宿舍喝酒吧！
-不要！
I'll give you two dollars -No!
-我會給你兩塊錢…-不要…
What the hell? Bastard!
…幹什麼？哪個渾蛋？
Sir Sugiura, how dare you!
衫浦大人…你膽子還真大！
Harassing a Mehebu woman?
敢欺負我馬赫坡的女人？
I was offering her a chance to earn
some extra money in our substation
…我只是讓她來駐在所賺外快…
It's no big deal
沒什麼大不了的嘛！
I know you Japanese policemen too well
你以為我不懂你們這些山地警察？
Take that blind prey of yours and scram
帶著那些瞎眼的獵物滾吧！
It's true, and she accepted it too
真的，她也答應了…
Another word from you
and I'll have the hounds feast on you
再講，我就放狗咬你！
Phooey! Fine, fine
哎呀…知道…知道了…
It's hard to reason with you savages
跟你們這群蕃人講不通啦！
You deserve it! Chicken!
活該…膽小鬼！
活該！
You're back, Sapu
薩布，你回來啦！
Chief, the matches you wanted
頭目，你要的火柴…
Sapu?
薩布…
Let the kids eat more meat. They're too skinny
讓孩子多吃點肉，都太瘦了…
Mouna! Mouna!
莫那…莫那…
Bakan,
why does Mouna need so many matches?
巴岡，莫那幹嘛一直在買火柴？
Who knows?
誰知道…
Had any meat, my boy?
有沒有吃肉呀？
Have a drink!
喝杯酒吧！
Father! Father!
父親…父親！
Father, can we slaughter a cow?
父親…再殺頭牛吧！
Not enough to eat?
不夠吃嗎？
It's enough, but we haven't had beef
for such a long time
夠！可是大家好久沒吃牛肉了…
Do it then
…那就殺吧！
Let's slaughter a cow!
再殺一頭牛啊！
Hooray! Let's slaughter a cow!
好啊！頭目…再殺一頭牛唷！
Baso, grab it!
巴索…抓好…
Grab its legs!
扳牠的腳…
Come on!
快點！
I've cut off the head
of the Japanese Governor-general
日本總督的頭被我拿下來了…
Wow! What a party!
哇！這麼熱鬧啊…
Sir Yoshimura
吉村大人…
Whose wedding day is it?
今天又是誰結婚啊？
It's Watan and Lubi's
是瓦旦和露比結婚…
Come! Have a drink with us, sir
來！大人，你也來杯小米酒吧！
No
不要！
No -Come on, have a drink
-不要！
-來啦，一起喝嘛！
No way
不要啦…
I don't drink the wine with your nasty saliva in it
我才不喝這種用口水做的髒酒！
Come on, have a drink
-I told you that I don't want to
-來啦，喝嘛！
-跟你講不要…
Your hand is all dirty with blood
小心你手上的血…
I invited you with good will
-You son-of-a-bitch!
-我這麼好意請你…
-你這傢伙…
You've soiled me with blood!
看你把我弄得都是血了…
I offered you a drink and you hit me?
請你喝酒，你怎麼打人呢？
I'll beat you into senses!
不明白我打到你明白！
Stop!
-I don't need to reason with a savage
-不要打了…
-我還聽生蕃講理？
What is it? Let's go look!
怎麼了？…過去看看！
Hurry up!
快點…
I know what you said just now
with a boar's head in your hand
你提豬頭喊什麼蕃話我聽不懂嗎？
Out of my way!
Say it again in Japanese if you dare
讓開…有本事你用日語講一遍啊…
Say it again!
你再講一遍啊！
Get out of my way! -I dare you!
-讓開…
-你敢不敢講啊？
Come on, guys!
大家過去！
Faster!
跑快一點！
Tado!
達多…
Baso, kill him!
巴索…打死他…
I'm holding down his feet! Beat him up!
我抓住他的腳了，你們用力打！
I'm holding down his feet again!
我又抓住他的腳了…
Stop! All of you!
住手！…通通住手！
What is it? What the hell?
怎麼會這樣？搞什麼東西呀？
Let me cut off this pig head of yours!
看我砍下你這顆豬頭…
Stop! Stop! Yoshi..
不要打了…不要打了…吉…
Yoshimura
吉村…
You're in big trouble
你們完蛋了…
You have the nerve to beat me up
-Let's kill him!
竟然敢打我！
殺了他！
Shut your mouth!
你閉嘴！
Excuse us! Let us through!
借過…借過…
I'll kill all you Mehebu clansmen
…我一定要殺光你們馬赫坡！
I'll kill you all
…我一定會殺光你們馬赫坡！
Let's do it, Father,
before the Japanese kill us all
父親，先動手吧！
他們不會放過我們的！
Why the hell did you provoke him
when you knew he'd kill us all?
你明知道他們不會放過我們
你還要去惹他？
You're nothing but a bunch of hounds
你們這群只懂追獵…
that can only chase and hunt
and know nothing of self-restraint
不懂控制的獵犬！
How much longer do I have to put up with you?
我要忍耐你們到什麼時侯？
Out of my way!
讓開…讓開…
Now you're here to bribe me with wine?
現在才想到拿酒來求我？
It's too late
來不及了！
I've filed the report on the case
of you beating up a police officer
毆打巡查的案子我已經呈報上去了
Tell you something..
告訴你…
This time I'll destroy your clan
我一定要毀了你們整個部落！
Yoshimura..
吉村…
I, Mouna Rudo, come here to
apologize to you personally
我莫那魯道親自來跟你道歉
Stop being so arrogant
你別太不給臉…
Who do you think you are?
莫那魯道又怎樣！
You think you're still a chief?
你還像個頭目嗎？
You can't even control your own sons
連自己的兒子都管不好
I don't think you're qualified
to be a chief anymore
還有資格當頭目？
Get out!
出去！出去！
Who the hell let you in?
誰跟你說可以進來的
Get the hell out!
都給我滾出去！
I don't want to see your faces again
我不要再看到你們…
Go home and rot!
回家等死吧！
Hey! Why did you do that to him?
-Shut up!
喂！你們幹嘛打他呢？
閉嘴！
I couldn't sleep last night because of a mosquito
被一隻蚊子搞到整晚睡不著！
Really? I'll see to it
是喔，那我再去了解一下…
Mr. Hanaoka!
花岡先生
Yes?
是！
May I know which clan you grew up in?
請問你是哪一個蕃社長大的？
Gungu Clan
荷戈社！
And your original name?
本名呢？
Dakis Nawi
…達奇斯那威
達奇斯那威…
We have another savage policeman
named Hanoka Ichiro
我們還有個叫花岡一郎的蕃人警察
He is the highest educated policemen here
是所有山地警察中學歷最高的
What are you doing this afternoon?
…你下午有事要忙嗎？
I'm going home for some private matter
…我等一下有事情需要回家一趟
I was to ask you
to patrol all the savage clans with us
原本想請你陪我到各蕃社去視察
and tell me the relationships among them all
順便幫我介紹各蕃社的關係…
Come with us! -No, it's alright
-你先陪我們去嘛！
-沒關係…！
It's alright
沒關係的！
Do whatever you need to do
你先去辦你的事吧！
It's alright
沒關係！
Kabasawa will go with us -Yes
-樺澤會和我們去！
-是的！
He knows the savages well too
他也是個蕃通！
Yoshimura has reported
Tado's case to the substation
吉村已經把達多的案子…
上報到分室來了！
I can't believe this Yoshimura
這個吉村也真是的…
Chief Mouna apologized to him personally
莫那頭目都親自去道歉了
Why did he insist on filing the case?
怎麼還硬要把案子往上送！
Yoshimura and Sugiura are not the same
as Kojima after all
吉村和衫浦，畢竟不是小島
They will never try to understand our people
是不會花心思去了解族人
If Kojima were living in Mehebu
there wouldn't be so much trouble
如果小島在馬赫坡的話…
這事就算發生，也不會這麼嚴重
Since I was very little
從小到大…
I've always been scared of Chief Mouna
我一看到莫那頭目都會害怕
It looks as if underneath his mantle
he's always gripping his machete
總覺得他藏在披風裡的手
ready to draw it to kill anytime
是隨時握著刀準備獵殺的！
He's no ordinary man
不能小看他…
He's impossible to be tamed
他是不可能被馴服的！
It must be difficult for him to torn between
the expectations of his fellow tribesmen
夾在族人期望和日本人威脅之間
and the intimidation of the Japanese
生活是很痛苦的！
Aren't we living like that as well?
我們兩個不也是這樣子嗎？
We don't want to be savages
…不想當野蠻人
but however hard
we try to dress up like the Japanese
但不管怎麼努力裝扮
we'll always be seen as uncivilized people
也改變不了這張不被文明認同的臉
We've lived like this for 20 years
已經忍了二十年了
Another 20 years won't be impossible
就再忍個二十年吧！
By the time our children grow up
等我們的孩子長大…
maybe we will have changed forever
the savage image of ours
或許就能徹底改變我們的野蠻形象
Do we still have the chance?
忍得了嗎？
Mehebu Clan may be wiped out soon
馬赫坡就要被趕盡殺絕了…
Father, let's fight the Japanese
父親…和日本人拚了吧！
Ouch! It hurts! -You dumb ass!
-燙…好燙啊…
-混帳東西！
Father, don't be mad!
父親…不要生氣…
Father! -You never learn!
-父親…父親…
-講不聽！
Enough! -You moron!
-好了…夠了啦…
-混帳東西！
Oh no! How come..
糟糕…怎麼…
It's the temporary bamboo bridge
that the savages used in the past
那是蕃人以前使用的竹便橋
It's ugly and insecure,
又醜又不堅固
but they keep walking over it
可是他們還老是要走那邊…
I'll tear it down sooner or later
哪天我直接把它給拆了！
But it saves them lots of time
if they walk over it to fetch water or to the field
其實他們提水或是到田裡…
都還是走那邊比較方便呀！
Look! This wire bridge is strong and firm
你看這鐵線橋做得這麼堅固！
Tado?
達多…
This young man is Tado Mouna
這個年輕人叫達多莫那
the eldest son of the Mehebu chief Mouna Rudo
是馬赫坡社頭目莫那魯道的長子
But he saw us without saying anything
Is there anything wrong with him?
他見到我們怎麼沒有任何表示？
是不是有什麼問題？
No, it's a habit of the savages
-It's not a very good habit
沒事！這是蕃人的習慣！
這不是很好的習慣！
Oh well, they're savages after all
…因為他們是生蕃嘛！
Can you stop talking about them like that?
你可以不要一直用這種口氣嗎？
Sugiura! -Welcome, sirs
-衫浦…
-主任、課長，歡迎！
This is Officer Sugiura
這位是衫浦巡查…
This way please
請往這邊走！
You should've informed me
before you came here, sir
課長要來怎麼不先通知呢？
I could've asked those savages
to welcome you with dances
我可以叫這些蕃人來跳舞歡迎啊！
No need for that
不用麻煩了…
We're only showing our hospitality
哎呀！課長怎麼這樣客氣呀！
Chief Mouna!
莫那頭目…
What?
幹嘛？
Chief Mouna,
莫那頭目…
can you tell me something about Japan?
跟我說說日本內地的事吧！
I know you've been there before
我知道你去過日本！
They have armies, cannons, machineguns
…日本有軍隊、大砲和機關槍…
airplanes and large steamers in Japan
飛機和大輪船…
There are more Japanese people
than the tree leaves in the forest
日本人比森林的樹葉還要繁密
than the pebbles in Jhuoshuei River
比濁水溪的石頭還多！
I know why you're asking me this
我也知道你問這些…
You don't really want to know Japan
並不是真的想知道那裡的事
All you want is to remind me
how powerful the Japanese are
你只是要提醒我日本有多厲害而已
Don't worry. I'll never forget
你放心吧！我不會忘記的！
Humph! You Japanese policemen
took us on the ship for days to Japan
哼！你們這些日本警察…
帶我們坐好幾天的船去日本
but all they showed us
were airplanes and cannons
卻只讓我們看飛機、大砲…
However, the policemen in Japan
不過…
were much nicer and kinder
than those of you here
那邊的警察比你們山地警察好多了
They feared we'd revolt against them
so they tried their best to befriend us
他們擔心反抗，想盡辦法對我們好
But those of you here in the mountains
但是你們這些山地日本警察
always provoke us so much
that I want to hunt your heads
卻總是壞得讓我想出草！
Chief Mouna, I'm still a Seediq
莫那頭目，我還是一個賽德克啊！
Although I'm now a Japanese policeman
雖然我是日本警察
I never forget
that the same blood runs in our veins
但我沒忘記我和你們流著一樣的血…
Dakis, when you die
are you entering a Japanese shrine?
達奇斯…
你將來要進日本人的神社？
Or the heavenly home of our ancestors?
還是我們祖靈的家？
I heard that..
…我聽說了
in the school for savage children
you beat up our kids like the Japanese do
你在蕃童教育所裡…
像日本人一樣地打著我們的孩子！
I beat them up because I don't want
the Japanese to look down on them
我打他們是希望…
…希望他們不要被日本人瞧不起！
You graduated from Normal School
你師範學校畢業
You're more highly-educated
than any other Japanese policemen
學歷比其他的日本警察還高
But how come you get the lowest salary?
為什麼你領的薪水是最低的？
Don't the Japanese look down on you already?
日本人瞧得起你嗎？
Beating up your own people makes them
look down on you even more
…自己打自己才會讓人瞧不起！
During our stay in Japan
以前去日本觀光的時侯
the Japanese knew all of us chiefs
from different clans hated one another
日本人明知道我們族群間有仇恨…
but they made us sit together
at the dining table deliberately
還故意安排我們坐在一起吃飯
We were glaring at one another
all the time while we were eating
讓我們每個人邊吃飯邊瞪著對方
intending to draw our machetes and kill
恨不得馬上拔刀殺了對方！
Humph! The Japanese are good at these things
哼，這些日本人就是懂這個…
Chief, is it so bad to be ruled by the Japanese?
頭目，被日本統治不好嗎？
At least we're leading a civilized life
我們現在文明的過生活
We have schools and post offices
有教育所，有郵局
and we don't have to survive
by hunting savagely anymore
不必再像從前一樣…
得靠野蠻的獵殺才能生存
Is it so bad to be ruled by the Japanese?
…被日本人統治不好嗎？
Is it so good to be ruled by them?
被日本人統治好嗎？
Our men are forced to bend over
to carry logs on our backs
男人被迫彎腰搬木頭
and our women have to kneel down
to serve and pour wine
女人被迫跪著幫傭陪酒
And all the money ends up
in the pockets of the Japanese policemen
該領的錢全進了日本警察的口袋
I'm a chief
我這個當頭目的…
but all I can do is get drunk
and pretend I see nothing and hear nothing
除了每天醉酒假裝看不見、聽不見
What else can I do?
還能怎麼樣？
Post offices? Stores? Schools?
郵局？商店？學校？
Do any of those things
make our lives easier and better?
什麼時侯讓族人的生活過得更好？
Instead,
we're made to see how impoverished we are
反倒讓他們看見自己有多貧窮了！
Chief, can't we bear it for another 20 years?
頭目…
我們再忍個二十年好嗎？
In 20 years, there will be no Seediq
and there will be no hunting ground
再二十年就不是賽德克！
就沒有獵場！
All our children will have turned Japanese
孩子全都是日本人了！
Chief Mouna,
…莫那頭目…
have you made up your mind to do it?
你真的要幹了嗎？
Chief Mouna?
莫那頭目…
About Yoshimura... -I'm old
-毆打吉村的事…
-我已經老了…
Don't worry
放心吧！
The Japanese are far too powerful
日本人這麼厲害
I won't go against them
我不敢怎樣的…
Go home
你回去吧！
This is the hunting ground
that belongs to me only
這裡是我一個人的獵場…
Get lost
你走開！
Chief... -Get lost!
-頭目…
-走開！
Dakis, have a drink
達奇斯…喝酒吧！
Go home and get yourself dead-drunk
回家以後喝它個大醉吧！
We can't drink anymore
不能再喝了…
We already... -Drink!
-我們已經…
-喝吧！
The millet wine that we make
我們釀的酒…
can set our people free
可以讓人無拘無束
making them sing and dance,
cry and laugh freely
讓人唱歌跳舞、哭笑隨性！
You'll see once you're drunk
大醉一場之後你就會懂了！
Go home now
回去吧！
Mouna!
莫那…
Father?
…父親…
Mouna, the tattoos on your face
are still so dark and clear
莫那！
你臉上的刺紋還是這麼的深黑…
You're indeed a Seediq Bale
你果然是一個賽德克巴萊！
You're a true hero
一個真正的英雄哪！
Mouna? Look at the lines on that rock
…莫那！
It split into half
when struck by the lightening, didn't it?
你看那巨石的線條…
是被雷光削開的吧！
In the dim light at dusk
the lightening splits a rock into half
昏黑的天色下…雷光削巨石…
What a beautiful sight!
多美麗的畫面啊！
Father?
父親…
I can't keep the intruders away
我阻止不了異族人…
(Ah, it's for real)
啊~真的啊！
(Here l am)
我來到這裡
(l used to guard these mountains
and forests bravely)
我曾英勇守護的山林…
(Oh yes, it's for real)
真的呀…是真的！
Mouna, let's sing
莫那…
來唱歌吧！
We haven't sung together for long
好久沒一起唱歌了！
(Reminisce the people from the past)
懷念過去的人們啊…
(Here l am)
我來到這裡
(l used to guard these mountains
and forests bravely)
我曾英勇守護的山林…
(These are our mountains)
這是我們的山唷…
(These are our creeks)
這是我們的溪唷…
(We're the true Seediq Bale)
我們是真正的賽德克巴萊唷…
(We go hunting in the mountains)
我們在山裡追獵…
(We share food in our clan)
我們在部落裡分享
(We fetch water from the creeks)
我們在溪流裡取水…
(l'm willing to give my life for these)
願我為此獻出生命…
(Oh, creek! Be quiet)
溪流啊！不要再吵了…
(Sisin babblers are singing)
祖靈鳥在唱歌了…
(Sing us a beautiful song please)
請唱首好聽的歌吧！
(Sing for our people)
為我們的族人唱…
(a song of our ancestral spirit)
來自祖靈的歌…
(l'm willing to give my life too)
願我也獻出生命！
(When the lightening rifts the rock)
巨石雷光下
(a rainbow appears)
彩虹出現了…
(and a proud man emerges)
一個驕傲的人走來了…
(Who is this man so proud?)
是誰如此驕傲啊？
(lt's your offspring)
是你的子孫啊…
(A Seediq Bale)
賽德克巴萊！
What?
什麼！
Tado Mouna became a hero before I did
達多怎麼比我先當上英雄了！
Those Japanese are outrageous
這些日本人實在太可惡了！
I can't believe they beat up someone
who offers them a drink
連請他喝酒都要被打…
A while ago..
上一次…
three girls from Boarung Clan
were asked to serve them drinks
波阿崙社有三個女孩被叫去陪酒
and they were raped
還被強暴！
Why couldn't Tado be a real hero
…達多既然想當英雄
and kill Yoshimura right on the spot?
怎麼不直接把吉村給殺了！
Kill him?
殺了他？
Don't you remember how my family died?
…我的家人怎麼死的？
難道你們忘了嗎？
My father killed only one Japanese man
我父親只殺了一個日本人
and they burned my whole family alive
我們全家人就被大火給活活燒死…
I was hiding in the woods watching
那時我躲在樹林裡…
without even blinking my eyes
可是連眼睛都沒眨一下…
So..
所以…
that's why we can't kill only one Japanese man
絕對不能只殺掉一個日本人…
We have to kill all of them to make a difference
一定要殺光所有的日本人才行！
Are you kidding me?
你在開玩笑嗎？
We wouldn't still be sitting here
if we could kill them all
如果殺得完的話
我們為什麼還要忍到現在？
Now the Mehebu chief Mouna Rudo
is driven to bay
因為今天馬赫坡的莫那魯道…
by that policeman from the lumberyard
被製材所的小警察逼上了絕路！
and the day after tomorrow on October 27th
is the big sports day
後天十月二十七日霧社舉行運動會…
By then, all the Japanese in Wushe
are going to gather in one place
到時霧社所有的日本人…
都會集合在一起…
Is it time already?
時侯真的到了嗎？
Father, there won't be a better chance
父親！等不到更好的機會了！
And we have no other choice
這是最後的路了…
We can't have the Japanese look down
on us anymore
不要再讓日本人看不起我們
We need to show them what we're made of
要讓他們知道我們也不是好惹的！
Let's fight them, Chief
頭目，和他們拚了吧！
Yeah! Let's fight them
對！跟他們拚了吧…
Young men..
年輕人…
I hate the Japanese no less than you do
我對日本人的仇恨
不會少於你們…
But do you realize that
只是你們知道行動之後…
we're going to die after all this
and all our people will be wiped out?
我們一定會死…甚至滅族嗎？
Our ancestors shed their blood
in exchange for our lives
我們的生命是祖先染血換來的
Now we're taking our children along
to the battlefield to shed blood
我們也要帶著子孫們一起染紅戰衣！
We're Seediq Bale, aren't we?
我們是賽德克巴萊呀！
Temu, does your father know you're here?
泰牧…
你父親知道你過來嗎？
My father told me that I should ask Chief Mouna
我父親告訴我…
請莫那頭目幫忙…
to help us youngsters get our faces tattooed
在孩子們的臉上作印記！
so that the ancestors' spirits
guarding the rainbow bridge
讓彩虹橋上的祖靈
will recognize us as the true Seediqs
永遠認得我們這些真正的賽德克…
Father?
父親…
If we want revenge,
it'd be the business of Mehebu Clan alone
如果說復仇，那是我馬赫坡的事
But if we're offering a blood sacrifice
to our ancestors
但是如果要血祭祖靈的話…
it will be the business of all the 12 clans
in Wushe
霧社十二個部落全部都要參加…
Keep it a secret before action
行動前先守住秘密！
We must tell none of the elders,
children or women in all these clans
所有部落裡的老人、小孩、女人
When did you..
-都不能知道…
-這是甚麼時侯…
I'm speaking here. Are you listening?
我講話…有沒有在聽啊？
Keep it a secret before action
行動前先守住秘密…
I knew Chief Mouna had a plan already
我就知道莫那頭目早有計劃…
What do you know?
It's your idea and your responsibility
你又知道什麼？你起的頭你負責…
Inform the chiefs of all the 12 clans
聯絡十二個血盟部落的頭目…
Tomorrow morning..
明天上午…
we're going to gather in Wushe
一起在霧社集合
and offer a blood sacrifice
…血祭祖靈！
Our ancestors' spirits..
祖靈們！
We're here for the guns. Sorry to disturb you
我們來取槍，無意打擾你們！
Boss.. -Welcome. This way please
-老闆…
-歡迎…裡面請…
Fill them up with salt
And give me ten boxes of matches
鹽…裝滿…火柴十盒…
Wow! Lots of things to buy, huh?
買這麼多？
Boss, we'll pay for it next time
老闆…這個先欠著吧？
On credit again?
又要欠錢？
Yes, we can -How much is it?
-可以的啦…
-老闆…這多少錢？
No, you can't!
不行不行！
Wait! You're buying all these on credit?
等一下…你們這些全部都要欠喔？
It's alright
沒關係啦…
It's alright? But you never pay me back!
沒關係…沒關係…你們有還過嗎？
Let's give them a hand
到外面幫忙！
That old drunkard Mouna Rudo
really can't take it anymore?
莫那魯道這老酒鬼真的忍不住了？
I'll ask the young men to get ready
before they all get dead drunk
我去召集年輕人準備了
要不然醉光就麻煩了
Young man, how dare you tell me these
年輕人…
你好大的膽子呀…
in front of the police station!
在駐在所前跟我說這些…
Good morning!
早安啊！
Pihu Sapu?
比荷沙波…
What the hell was he up to?
這小子在幹嘛？
That crazy boy spells nothing but trouble
整天瘋瘋癲癲的只會惹事…
But we'd be bored around here
without him, won't we?
不過…如果山上少了他
應該會很無趣吧！
You call making troubles interesting?
到處惹事叫有趣嗎？
Tado, look! Only the gun barrel is left
達多，你看…
都爛成這樣了！
No, I won't do it -Won't do it?
我不答應！
不答應？
Chief Dahdo..
塔道頭目
the chiefs of the other clans
have all agreed to join us
其他部落頭目都答應了
and everything is ready now
我們也都準備計劃好了
Fighting the Japanese will lead us to death only
和日本軍隊拚只有死路一條
We've had three chiefs in our family
that died of fighting the Japanese
我們家族三代頭目都為抗日而死
Now we've stooped to bring you kids up
今天…
to carry on the lifeline of our people
not to get killed on the battlefield
我們辛苦忍辱把你們這些孩子養大
是為了要保住族群命脈
不是要你們去求死的！
Chief... -We're not afraid of death
-頭目 -我們不怕死！
Even Chief Mouna agreed to do it
人家連莫那頭目都答應了！
Chief Dahdo, they'll laugh at us if you don't do it
塔道頭目…
你這樣人家會笑我們的
They can laugh at me for all I care
笑我怕死也沒關係
I'll never allow our Gungu Clan
to join the battle. Period
我就是不准我荷戈社參戰！
But Chief.. -Chief!
頭目…頭目…
頭目！
Are you going to be a hunter
forever without guns or hunting grounds?
難道你要永遠當一個…
沒有槍、沒有獵場的獵人嗎？
You have no tattoo on your face
Don't forget whom you're talking to
你這個沒有圖騰的孩子…
不要忘了你的身份！
What do we do now?
現在怎麼辦呢？
I can't stand that old man
真受不了這個老頭子…
No way
不可能！
I won't allow our young clansmen
我不會讓我們的年輕人
to sacrifice themselves in vain
with you maniacs
陪著你們這些瘋子去白白犧牲…
But.. -I won't let out this secret of yours
可是…
我不會把你們的秘密說出去的…
Go home
你回去吧！
You only show off your bravery
with those animal skulls now?
你現在只靠獸骨炫耀你的勇敢嗎？
Chief Walis, you once fought the Japanese
at Hakaw Supeitei
瓦力斯頭目…
當年在人止關
Where's your bravery now?
你對抗日本人的英勇哪裡去了？
Bravery? I gave it all to you long ago
英勇？
…我全部都已經留給你了！
Bring your women and children here
to our Paran Clan
把女人孩子帶過來我們巴蘭社吧！
to keep the bloodline of your clan
替你們部落留些人口…
A clan so big...with so many people..
這麼大的一個部落
這麼多的人…
What are you doing?
你們在幹嘛？
Hello, sir!
大人好！
Come closer
靠中間站一點…
Stop fooling around!
Go home and clean your places up
不要嘻皮笑臉，快回去整理環境！
Yes, sir
好
Go on!
快走！
Sorry
對不起…
Stay away, kids
那邊的小朋友讓開…
Okay, ready
好！那要拍囉！
One, two, three
一、二、三！
I'm not going in
我就送你們到這裡了！
Make me proud in tomorrow's games
明天加油喔…
Can you stay with us, Father?
父親也留下來嘛！
No, I can't. I have to go back before dark
不行…
父親再不回去，要天黑了…
You're spending the night here
Be a good boy, you hear?
晚上睡別人家裡要乖喔…
懂不懂？
See you then
那我走了！
Bye -Take care
再見！
小心慢走…
Let's go!
我們走吧！
Excuse me!
不好意思…
Mouna knows everything about battles
…莫那…
這傢伙確實懂得戰鬥…
But I'm old. I can't go with him
不過我已經老了，不能陪他去了…
But..
-But our Drodux Clan won't be absent in this
可是…
可是我們羅多夫是不會缺席的…
Do I have to say it again in Japanese?
…要我說日本話嗎？
Good morning!
早安…早安…
Pihu! What's wrong with you?
比荷！搞什麼啊你？
Pihu!
比荷…
Good morning!
早…安…
Why did you get all our hounds
to bark like crazy?
你幹嘛惹得我整個部落狗吠…
Chief Mouna, didn't you say
that you wouldn't do it?
莫那頭目，你不是說你不會幹嗎？
Do what? Who says I'm doing anything?
要幹什麼？…誰跟你說我要幹的？
Dakis, you're nothing
but a police dog wearing a collar
達奇斯…
你這隻戴著項圈的警犬…
Did your master send you here
as a persuader?
你的主人派你來勸降的嗎？
-Tado!
達多！
Dakis, you haven't answered
my question from last time
達奇斯…
你上次還沒有回答我
When you die,
are you entering a Japanese shrine
你將來要進日本人的神社
or the heavenly home of our ancestors?
還是我們賽德克祖靈的家？
Are you Dakis? Or Hanaoka Ichiro?
你是達奇斯？還是花岡一郎？
I'm a true Seediq tribesman. I am!
我是真正的賽德克！我是…
But...
-If you are, take off your uniform
-可是…
-是的話就換掉這身衣服
and offer blood sacrifice to our ancestors
with us tomorrow
明天和我們一起血祭祖靈！
You know well
how many soldiers the Japanese have
你又不是不知道日本軍隊有多少…
You're going to get killed for nothing
這麼做只不過是白白犧牲而已…
You told me the other day that there are
more Japanese people than..
你上次不是還說日本人比森林裡的…
There are more Japanese people
than the tree leaves in the forest
日本人比森林的樹葉還要繁密…
than the pebbles in Jhuoshuei River
比濁水溪裡的石頭還要多…
But my determination to fight them
is more adamant than Mt. Chilai
但我反抗的決心比奇萊山還要堅定！
If your civilization wants us to cringe
如果你的文明是叫我們卑躬屈膝
I'll show you the pride of savages
那我就帶你們看見野蠻的驕傲！
The true Seediq tribesmen
真正的賽德克…
Listen carefully, Dakis
達奇斯…
You being a Seediq descendant
who never tried to understand yourself
你這從來不想了解自己的子孫聽好…
A Seediq Bale can lose his body
賽德克巴萊可以輸去身體…
but he fights to keep his soul at all cost
但是一定要贏得靈魂！
A Seediq who loses his soul
輸去靈魂的賽德克…
will be forsaken by our ancestors' spirits
一定會遭到祖靈遺棄！
Do you understand..
你懂了嗎？
..my child?
…孩子啊！
There are over 130 guns
in the Wushe substation
…霧社分室裡有一百三十幾枝槍
and many boxes of ammunition too
還有好幾箱彈藥…
On the sports day tomorrow
明天運動會的時侯
Jiro...Dakis Nawi will be on duty
二郎…達奇斯那威值勤
I'll tell him everything beforehand
我會先跟他講好…
Father, will he betray us?
父親，他會不會跑去密告啊？
No, he won't
他不會的！
Can't believe all the gunpowder
I spent years collecting will go to waste
害我白白準備了那麼多年的火藥…
What is it, Pihu? -They're all cowards!
比荷，怎麼樣了？
都是些膽小鬼啦！
Chief, only six clans are willing to join us
頭目…
只有六個社願意參加
A little more than 300 men in all
-300 men?
人數也才三百多個人而已！
…三百人？
I tried so hard to persuade them
我一直講一直講…
I was so incensed that
I nearly drew my machete
講到我獵刀都快拔出來了
But they... -Take it easy
-可是他們…
-你放輕鬆…
It's quite enough to have 300. Go home quietly
Chief..
頭目…
三百個夠了…
全部都安安靜靜的離開
Don't get caught before action
-Chief..
-別還沒行動就被抓了…
-頭目…
Get out of here. All of you
出去…全部離開…
Get out!
出去！
(Why do men belittle women so?)
你們男人為何要這樣欺負女人…
(Don't forget all the pride you boast of)
別忘了所有你們自誇的驕傲
(comes from us women)
都是來自我們女人
(lt is us who weave your glory)
是我們女人為你們所編織的呀！
(lt is us women behind men's tattoos of bravery)
是女人成就了男人英勇的圖騰呀！
The sun..
太陽…
(l'm on my way)
我正在路上
(to the heavenly home of our ancestors)
我要走向祖靈之家了
(We'll be back as brothers)
讓我帶你回來成為兄弟吧！
(Hark!)
聽著吧！
(Behold!)
看著吧！
(My soul fights in the falling leaves)
我的靈魂如松葉紛飛
(l am Mouna Rudo)
我是莫那魯道
(l bring home the innocent souls)
而如今提領著無邪的魂魄回來了…
(Young warriors)
年輕的勇士啊…
(No one can defeat us)
沒人能抵抗我們！
(Oh, our warriors)
我們的勇士啊…
(much like the budding pine leaves)
像松枝嫩芽般的勇士啊…
You don't think I know
what you men are up to, do you?
你以為我看不出來…
你們男人在計畫什麼？
I'm the chief's daughter
我是頭目的女兒…
Wherever you're going
the children and I will follow
不管你將來去哪裡
我和孩子一定都要在你身邊
Your job is to guard this firepan
and keep the fire burning
你儘管守好火盆，別讓火熄了
When it's time to leave
I'll take you along with me
該離開的時侯，我不會丟下你們…
Yamada!
山田…
Sugiura, get out of there!
衫浦…你給我出來…
Come on, coward
-Who is it? What's going on?
-膽小鬼出來…
-是誰？怎麼了？
What's going on?
怎麼回事？
Stop! Who is it?
你住手…誰啊？
Baso, what the hell?
巴索…你在搞什麼？
What the hell are you doing?
Are you out of your mind?
你到底在幹什麼？你想死啊！
Shut up!
閉嘴！
(Do you know who l am?)
知道我是誰嗎？
(l'm Tado Mouna, a true warrior)
我是達多莫那！真正的勇士！
(When you bleed, the animosity)
(between you and me no longer exists)
當你流出血，你我的仇恨從此消失…
(l'm a true warrior)
我就是真正的勇士
(l'm a Seediq Bale, a true warrior)
我是賽德克巴萊，真正的勇士
(Your soul is welcome to dwell with me)
歡迎你的靈魂居住在我這裡
(l'll feed you with millet wine and foods)
我會拿酒及食物供養你
(There's no longer hatred between us)
我們之間不再有仇恨
(When you bleed, the animosity)
(between you and me no longer exists)
當你流出血，你我的仇恨從此消失…
(You'll be with our ancestors' spirits)
你也要和我們的祖靈一起
(to watch over my people)
守護我們族人…
Lubi, keep the fire burning
露比，別讓火熄了…
I'll be home before dark
我天黑就回來…
Women! Children! Why aren't you singing?
女人呀！孩子呀！
為什麼不唱歌呢？
Sing!
唱歌啊…
唱歌啊！
Mouna!
莫那…
My old friend!
我的老朋友！
Mouna! Chief Mouna!
莫那…莫那頭目…
Shut up!
閉嘴…閉嘴！
Not you
我不是在說你…
Tanah, split your men into two teams
達那哈…
把你們的人分成兩隊
You lead one team along Bkasan River
to annihilate all the police stations
你帶一隊沿著布砍散溪
消滅所有沿線的駐在所
and cut off the communication
of the Japanese to the east
切斷日本人東邊的聯絡線
The other team follows me to Gungu Clan
to meet up with other clans
另一隊跟我一起到荷戈社…
和其他部落會合！
What do we do
after those police stations are annihilated?
那我們消滅了那些駐在所之後呢？
After that? Come to Mehebu Clan for a drink
之後？…到我馬赫坡來喝酒！
Chief Mouna!
莫那頭目！
Where are they? Aren't they here yet?
人呢？都到嗎？
They're all here
都到了…
but Chief Dahdo doesn't allow
our Gungu Clan to join in the battle
但是塔道頭目不准我們荷戈社參戰
Everyone's trying to convince him
大家都在勸塔道頭目！
Have all the police stations been annihilated?
駐在所打下來沒有？
We've burned down every one of them
都燒光了！
Then why waste our time persuading him?
那還跟他囉嗦什麼！
I said no
不行就是不行…
Our clan is big. We must join in
我們這麼大的部落怎麼可以不參戰
Chief Dahdo..
塔道頭目…
even a boar fights back when driven to bay
Why don't you understand?
山豬都懂得反擊，為什麼你不懂？
I'd rather be punished by the Japanese
than have our whole clan wiped out
我寧可被日本人處罰，也不能滅族
My children, don't you remember
how your fathers died?
你們這些孩子…
忘了你們父親是怎麼死去的嗎？
No one from our Gungu Clan is allowed to go
我荷戈社任何一個人都不准參加！
Are you frightened to death by the Japanese?
Or are you spoiled by them?
你到底是被日本人嚇壞了？
還是被日本人給慣壞了？
Chief! Chief Mouna!
頭目…莫那頭目…
You know well
that we're bound to lose this battle
你明明知道這一戰一定會輸
Why do you insist on fighting it?
為什麼還要打？
Because of our ancestral spirit
that's soon to be forgotten
為了快被遺忘的圖騰！
Look at these young men
你看這些年輕人
Their faces are clean without the Seediq tattoos
白白淨淨的臉…
沒有賽德克該有的圖騰
Do you want to see their souls
forsaken by our ancestors' spirits?
你忍心看著他們死去的靈魂
被祖靈遺棄？
Or don't you think they're qualified
還是你覺得他們不夠資格
to be Seediq Bale
with hands stained with blood?
成為一個雙手染血的賽德克巴萊？
Ancestral spirit?
圖騰？
Ancestral spirit!
圖騰！
You want to sacrifice their lives
in exchange for these tattoos
拿生命來換圖騰印記…
but what does it take to get
these young lives back?
那拿什麼來換回這些年輕的生命？
Pride!
驕傲！
Let's go!
出發！
Mr. Inspector, look! Here comes the mist!
督學先生…
你看，起霧了！
What a beautiful sight!
好美呀！
Here comes your brother. Good luck!
哥哥來了…加油…
Good luck!
加油！加油！
What a thick mist!
好濃的霧啊！
Yeah, it's often misty around here
是啊！這裡的天氣一向如此
But with a mist so thick
how will they judge the games?
可是這麼濃的霧…
待會怎麼判定比賽成績啊？
Those games are just for kids
Having fun is all that matters
小孩子的遊戲好玩就好了…
Come on, have more hot tea. It's chilly
來…再來杯熱茶，天氣冷…
Thank you
謝謝…
We still have time for a rest
還有點時間的…可以再休息一下！
Be careful! -I'm sorry
小心！
對不起…
Are you alright? -Yeah, thank you
沒事吧？
嗯…謝謝！
Let's do it. There's no turning back
行動吧！已經脫不了身了！
My children..
孩子們…
at the other end of the rainbow
in the heavenly home of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的彩虹彼端
lies a fertile hunting ground
還有一座肥美的獵場
Our ancestors are all there
我們的祖先可都在那兒哪！
Only brave souls are allowed to enter
那片只有英勇靈魂才能進入的獵場
It's the one hunting ground
we cannot afford to lose
絕對不能失去…
Fellow tribesmen!
族人啊…
My fellow tribesmen!
Let's hunt the heads of our enemies
我的族人啊！
獵取敵人的首級吧！
We can no longer keep the hunting ground
in the Wushe mountains
霧社高山的獵場我們是守不住了…
Let's wash our souls clean with blood
用鮮血洗淨靈魂！
Stride over the rainbow
to our eternal hunting ground
走進彩虹！永遠的獵場！
We're offering a blood sacrifice to our ancestors
這是在血祭祖靈…
Young men, let our ancestors' spirits
be possessed in your blades
年輕人…
讓祖靈寄居在你們的刀鋒中
Entrust your hatred to the clouds and mists
把你們的仇恨寄存在雲霧間
Let's do it
行動吧！
Be still! How many times do I have to tell you?
排個隊動來動去
要講幾次才會明白啊！
Go to the back of the line!
排到最後去！
No, it's not what you think
…其實不是這樣的…
Hello?
喂…
Really?
真的嗎？
How fair-spoken you are!
-No, you're too kind
你真是會說話啊！
沒有…沒什麼啦！
Hatsuko!
初子…
What the hell! Lower you voice
幹什麼啊？那麼大聲…
Hanaoka?
花岡…
It's your shift at the ammunition storage
彈藥庫叫你去換班了！
Hello
你好！
Your candies
這是你的糖…
Thank you
謝謝囉…
謝謝你喔！
Hanako!
花子！
Hello -Hello
-你好！
Wow! You bought candies
你買糖果啦？
So cute
好可愛喔…
Come on, let's go. Bye!
我們也走吧…再見！
Bye!
慢走！
It's Ichiro!
一郎耶！
Welcome! You've come a long way
歡迎你來！辛苦你了！
This way please -Thank you
-請走這邊…
-謝謝！
It's spectacular
好盛大的運動會啊…
All rise!
起立！
Be quiet!
安靜！
Sing the national anthem
唱國歌！
(Our Mikado rules the world)
吾皇禦世…
(For generations to come)
千秋萬代永存…
(Like sands accumulating to rocks)
猶如小石成岩…
Get him!
抓住他！
Stop!
不要跑！
不要逃！
What's going on?
發生什麼事啊？
Keep playing! Come on!
繼續彈…繼續啊…
Sing! Keep singing!
唱歌…繼續唱歌…
Keep singing!
繼續唱歌啊…
Play it!
快點彈…
Keep singing!
繼續唱歌…
(Like sands accumulating to rocks)
猶如小石成岩…
Get him!
抓住他！
Here comes the blood sacrifice!
血祭祖靈了！
Come on!
走…
Run! Come on!
快逃！快逃呀！
Hatsuko! Hatsuko!
初子…初子…
Hatsuko!
初子…
Come on! Unlock the storage
The savages are hunting heads
快！打開槍庫，蕃人出草…
Hanaoka!
花岡…
Unlock that one too!
快把那間也打開！
Chief Mouna, my wife Obing
is still dressed in kimono
莫那頭目…
我妻子歐嬪還穿著和服…
Shut up! Open the door!
閉嘴！去開門…
Run for your lives!
你們快逃！
I'm a descendant from a samurai as well
我也是武士的後裔呀…
Mr. Satsuka! -Mr. Commissioner!
-佐塚先生…
-郡守…
Mr. Satsuka! -Come on!
-佐塚先生…
-快一點啊…
Mr. Satsuka!
佐塚先生…
Hide in there! Be quiet!
快進去…安靜點…
Hush! Be quiet!
小聲一點不要出聲…
Aren't you a savage too?
Why are you hiding with us?
你不也是蕃人嗎？
幹嘛也跟我們一起躲？
We're offering blood sacrifice
What are you daydreaming for?
血祭祖靈了…發什麼呆呀！
Follow me!
跟我走！
Pawan! Pawan!
巴萬…
Come on! Hurry up!
快…快一點…
Missed! Come on!
沒中…快！
Damned Japanese! I'll make you weep!
可惡的日本人，看我今天讓你哭…
Come with me!
跟我走！
(Oh, my children, l know)
(我的孩子啊，我知道)
(ln those passionate days)
(在那激情奔放的日子裡
(You've learned a song)
(你們學會一首歌)
(To sing for the soon-be-forgotten ancestral spirit)
(為即將被遺忘的祖靈唱歌)
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
My children! What are you doing?
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
孩子啊！你們在做什麼？
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
What on earth are you doing, my children?
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
我的孩子啊，你們在做什麼？
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
(Your dynamic bodies
dance to our ancestors' spirits)
(你們躍動的身軀舞向祖靈靈)
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
Dahdo! Dahdo!
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
塔道…塔道…
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
Go to the school right now
to save your daughter Obing
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
快去公學校救你女兒歐嬪…
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
She's dressed in kimono
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
她穿著和服哪！
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
No! No!
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
不要…不要…
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
(No enemy dares to gaze at it)
(令敵人不敢直視)
Didn't we agree not to kill the Hans?
不是說別殺漢人嗎？
(But my children!)
What are you chasing him for?
-We did?
(But my children!)
Didn't we agree not to kill the Hans?
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
不是說別殺漢人嗎？
你還追什麼？…
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
有說過嗎？
(But my children!)
You'd better stay sober today!
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
你今天給我清醒一點！
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
(But my children!)
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
Don't throw anything hard stuff at me again!
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
下次別拿那硬硬的丟我…
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
Okay, fine
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
好好…
(The distant stars are nowhere to be seen)
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
(看不見遠方的星辰)
(The distant stars are nowhere to be seen)
Hush! Hush!
(看不見遠方的星辰)
安靜！安靜！
(Oh, see how the stars are dimming)
Hush! Hush!
(啊，那些星辰已漸漸垂滅)
安靜！安靜！
(Oh, see how the stars are dimming)
(啊，那些星辰已漸漸垂滅)
(My children!)
(我的孩子啊！)
(The chilling light reflected
off the tips of your machetes)
(你們刀尖的寒光)
(Makes the moon seem pale as wax )
(讓月亮蒼白如蠟
(The bloodstain on the tips of your machetes)
(你們刀尖的血漬)
Come on, Mr. Commissioner!
-I can't run anymore
(你們刀尖的血漬)
郡守，快點…
我跑不動了…
(Keeps the night fire burning bright)
What are you talking about? Come on!
(讓夜晚不停燃燒)
你在說什麼…
快點…
(Keeps the night fire burning bright)
(讓夜晚不停燃燒)
Get up!
起來…
(Keeps the night fire burning bright)
(讓夜晚不停燃燒)
Someone's here!
有人追過來了…
(Listen, children!)
Someone's here!
(聽啊，孩子們)
有人追過來了…
(Listen, children!)
I'm exhausted -This way!
Someone's here!
(聽啊，孩子們)
-我不行了…
-往這邊…這邊下去！
(Listen, children!)
I really can't run anymore!
(聽啊，孩子們)
我真的不行了…
(Listen, children!)
(聽啊，孩子們)
Mr. Kikukawa!
菊川先生…
(Listen, children!)
(聽啊，孩子們)
(The sound drifting down from the forest)
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
I don't want to die here!
我不要死在這裡呀…
(The sound drifting down from the forest)
Tado, don't shoot!
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
達多，別開槍！
(The sound drifting down from the forest)
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
Temu,
you'd do anything to become a hero, huh?
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
泰牧，你想當英雄想瘋了…
Temu,
you'd do anything to become a hero, huh?
泰牧，你想當英雄想瘋了…
(ls it the sigh of our ancestors' spirits?)
Temu,
you'd do anything to become a hero, huh?
(是祖靈的嘆息)
泰牧，你想當英雄想瘋了…
(ls it the sigh of our ancestors' spirits?)
(是祖靈的嘆息)
Look, I killed a high-ranking official
你看，我殺的可是大官哪！
(Or is it the sigh of the wind?)
Look, I killed a high-ranking official
(還是風的嘆息)
你看，我殺的可是大官哪！
(Or is it the sigh of the wind?)
(還是風的嘆息)
Where's the other one?
還有一個呢？
(Or is it the sigh of the wind?)
(還是風的嘆息)
(Listen, children!)
(聽啊，孩子們)
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
Pihu..
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
比荷…
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
Don't kill me. We're friends
-My friend..
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
不要殺我…我們是朋友…
我的朋友…
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
I'm not killing people
I'm offering blood sacrifice to our ancestors
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
我不是在殺人，我是在血祭祖靈…
I'm not killing people
I'm offering blood sacrifice to our ancestors
我不是在殺人，我是在血祭祖靈…
(ls it our ancestors' spirits weeping?)
I'm not killing people
I'm offering blood sacrifice to our ancestors
(是祖靈的哭泣)
我不是在殺人，我是在血祭祖靈…
(ls it our ancestors' spirits weeping?)
(是祖靈的哭泣)
(Or is it the clouds crying?)
(還是雲的哭泣)
Is that your teacher?
你們老師嗎？
(Or is it the clouds crying?)
(還是雲的哭泣)
(Oh, my children!)
(我的孩子啊！)
Teacher...My dear teacher..
老師…親愛的老師！
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
You think we're a bunch of cowards?
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
你以為我們很好欺負嗎？
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
I'm sorry. I was trying to educate you
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
對不起！我是在教育你們…
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
I'd punish a Japanese kid
when he makes mistakes
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
日本小孩犯錯我也有打呀！
(Look! The reddened earth is silent)
But you've been so mean to me!
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
可是你打我最兇！
(你們看，染紅的土地沈默不語)
(Look! The reddened earth is silent)
(Look! The bark of Pusu Qhuni is peeling off)
(你們看，波索康夫尼的樹皮一片片剝落)
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
You poor Japanese..
可憐的日本人…
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
Come to the heavenly home of our ancestors
and be our friends forever
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
一起到我們祖靈的天家
當永遠的朋友吧！
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
(Touch your angry forehead)
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
Come here! You go there!
過來這裡…你們去那邊！
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
Come here!
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
你過來！
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
Wait!
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
慢著…
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
Have you seen my daughter Obing?
有沒有看到我們家歐嬪？
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
No
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
沒有…
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
Han...I'm a Han! -Go there!
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
漢人…我是漢人…
去那邊！
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
Have you seen my daughter Obing?
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
有沒有看到我們家歐嬪？
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
Are you a Seediq from Toda?
你是道澤人？
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
Get lost!
你們走開…
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
Tell your chief Temu Walis
回去告訴鐵木瓦力斯
that we're offering blood sacrifice
to our Seediq ancestors
這是血祭整個賽德克的祖靈
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Wushe has fallen into our hands
we Seediqs from Tgdaya
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
that we're offering blood sacrifice
to our Seediq ancestors
(我的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
這是血祭整個賽德克的祖靈
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
霧社已經被我們攻下來了
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Those of you from Toda and Truku
should join us as well
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
叫你們道澤和托洛庫也一起加入！
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
Move over!
過去！過去…
(All the pinecones have broken in the wind)
Move over!
(森林中的松子已在風中全部碎裂)
過去！過去…
(All the pinecones have broken in the wind)
(森林中的松子已在風中全部碎裂)
(The teary moon stops you
from walking towards death)
(淚光閃閃的月亮橫在你們走向死亡的途中)
(The teary moon stops you
from walking towards death)
Chief Mouna?
(淚光閃閃的月亮橫在你們走向死亡的途中)
莫那頭目
(The teary moon stops you
from walking towards death)
(淚光閃閃的月亮橫在你們走向死亡的途中)
(The gloomy clouds cannot shelter the sadness)
Obing!
(暗鬱的雲朵已遮不住)
歐嬪…歐嬪…
(The gloomy clouds cannot shelter the sadness)
Obing!
(暗鬱的雲朵已遮不住)
歐嬪…歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Obing!
(暗鬱的雲朵已遮不住)
歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Obing!
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Jiro!
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
二郎…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Obing! -Jiro!
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
-歐嬪…
-二郎…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Obing! -I'm in here!
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
歐嬪…
我在這裡…
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Obing! -Help me!
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
-歐嬪…
-快點救我…
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Move away!
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
讓開！
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
Father!
父親…
(Time is light as a flame)
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
(時間輕如一朵火焰
(Time is light as a flame)
Father!
(時間輕如一朵火焰
父親…
(Time is light as a flame)
Why must you hunt heads?
(時間輕如一朵火焰
為什麼要出草…
(That lights up the stars in your souls)
Why must you hunt heads?
(你們靈魂裡的星星已被點燃)
為什麼要出草…
(That lights up the stars in your souls)
(你們靈魂裡的星星已被點燃)
(Your dreams are vast like a blue ocean)
(你們夢廣大如一片藍色海洋)
(But the joyous tears
in your souls have dried out)
(而你們的靈魂裡歡樂的淚水卻已乾涸)
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
(How much pain do you swallow to
sing the song of our ancestral spirit?)
(為唱出祖靈的歌需要吞下許多痛苦)
(How much shame do you swallow
to speak what you want to say?)
(為說出自己的話需要吞下許多屈辱)
(How much regret do you swallow
to fulfill your dreams?)
(為實現夢想需要吞下許多遺憾)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(孩子啊，你們怎麼了？)
(Oh, my children!
What exactly is wrong with you?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們到底怎麼了？)